so this is another agent
it's a simply called question and answer
there's a few questions from somebody
then who that is and there nothing sure
answers so the question question first question
so the question question first question
is there are those periods when our
hearts or mind happen to be absorbed in
things and become blemished or darkened
but we are still aware of ourselves such
as when some form of greed hatred and
delusion comes up although we know that
these things are objectionable we are
unable to prevent them from arising
could it be said that even as we are are
aware of them this is providing the
basis for increased clinging and
attachment and maybe is putting us
further back to where we started so I
said again could we say could could it
be said that even as we are aware of
them this is providing the basis for
this is providing the basis for
increased cleaning in attachment what is
their awareness of it or the thing in
itself being aware of it
that's providing basis for further
clinging yeah right maybe it's putting
us further back to where we started from
right but onion char says well can you
either get the question from the started
and let me say it first and then tell me
what I need char says so the question
begins they are those periods when our
minds happen to be absorbed in stings
and become blemished or darkened but we
are still aware of ourselves such as
when some form of greed hatred and
delusion comes up although we know that
these things are objectionable we are
unable to prevent them from arising yeah
that's it that's the wrong assumption
they're trying to prevent these things
from arising which means not seeing
where your responsibilities but
overdoing it trying to gather it trying
to prevent things from manifesting in
the first place but that's not a new
they cannot be on you so the response
your that's why they would get confused
in and an end up revolving around the
objectionable states
because they're overdoing the aspect of
trying to get rid of it and that's how
you bind yourself with it like a dog
that runs around the post trying to get
away from the post your scientists it's
tied to the post it tries to get away
from the post ends up being tighter and
tighter closer to the post so if that
person were to recognize that they can't
it's not up to you to prevent things
from manifesting or not that's not your
responsibility and that's not the
problem either but usually people
believe oh there is greed in my mind I
must get rid of it but that's not the
problem the problem is you acting out of
the greed out of a version and that's a
new so you have to be able to not
interfere with the thing that has
manifested on its own and then recognize
that that you know responsible for that
and that's not the issue and that's not
the greed in itself
that's the prospect of greed being
presented but it's you then choosing to
act by body speed remind delighting it
by with mental and delighting in it
welcoming it that you're doing so when
the Buddha says you shouldn't delight in
greed aversion delusion means that you
don't delight in what has presented
itself that doesn't mean I must get rid
of what has because that would mean that
you are in control the you are that you
do have a say as to what appears what
doesn't but the fact that if you were to
truly have a say these things wouldn't
have arisen in the first place
but they do arise on their own and you
have not saying yet you go around acting
like I have a say why because you don't
know where the problem is so you think
the problem is in manifestation and not
in the attitude your attitude towards
the manifestation so that's what the
restraint comes first not to prevent
things from arising but to enable you to
allow things to arise without acting out
of them towards them without acting out
of it out of that pressure of arising
and the more restrain you are means the
less interfering with things
manifestation you would be doing anyway
yeah I didn't charm answers that says
that's it one must keep knowing them at
that point that's the method of practice
knowing them in the point of their
arising yeah so the question asks I mean
that's simultaneously we are both aware
of them and repelled by them but lacking
the ability to resist them they just
burst forth become burst forth unless
you act you choose to act out of them
that's what they don't see pushing
forward yeah
the pressure might be yeah sure but no
matter the pressure can sort of make a
choice for you it's always you who
chooses to act out of the pressure which
means you can also choose not to act
which means you are the the the the
doorway through which the pressure can
enter because you are the one who opens
the door or doesn't not knowing that
then here you it feels like as if the
action came automatically out of the
pressure because you haven't practiced
restraint sufficiently not properly
enough so you haven't discerned that
line for which you're responsible after
which like you don't cross ensure
answers by then it's already beyond
one's capability to do anything that
point one has to readjust oneself and
then continue contemplation don't just
give up on them there and then when one
sees things arise in that way one tends
to get upset or feel regret but it is
possible to say that they are uncertain
and subject to change what happens is
that one sees these things are wrong but
one is still not ready to or able to
deal with them as if they are
independent entities the left over
karmic tendencies that are still
creating and conditioning the state of
the mind one doesn't wish to allow the
mind to become like that but it does and
it indicates that one's knowledge and
awareness you still neither sufficient nor fast
you still neither sufficient nor fast
enough to keep abreast of things one
must practice and develop mindfulness as
much as one can in order to gain a
greater and more penetrating awareness
whether the mind is soiled or blemished
in some way it doesn't matter what comes
up one should be contemplating firm
an uncertainty of it by maintaining this
contemplation if each instant that
something arises after some time one
will see the impermanent nature inherent
in all sense objects and mental states
because one sees them as such gradually
they will lose their importance and once
clinging and attachment to do that which
is a blemish on the on the mind will
continue to diminish whenever suffering
arises one will be able to work through
it and readjust oneself but one
shouldn't give up on this work or set it
aside one must keep up continuity of
effort and try to make one's awareness
fast enough to keep in touch with the
changing mental conditions it could be
said that so far one's divot it could be
said that so far one's development of
the path still lacks sufficient energy
to overcome the mental defilements
whenever suffering arises the hub the
mind becomes clouded over and one must
keep developing that knowledge and
understanding of the of that clouded
mind that is what one affects on one
must really take hold of it and
repeatedly contemplate that this
suffering and this contentment is not
just a sure thing it's something that is
ultimately impermanent unsatisfactory
and not self focusing on these three
characteristics whenever these
conditions of suffering arise again one
will know them straight away how many
experienced them before and gradually
little by little once practice should
gain momentum and as time passes
whatever since objects and mental state
arise will lose their value in this way
once harden will know them for what they
are and accordingly put them down having
reached a point where one is able to
know things and put them down with ease
she didn't actually well he didn't
actually provided direct answer to the
question he was I mean it's fine but you
could see was talking around as in well
you just have to keep practicing which
is true but you could have answered it
more accurately and point out to a
person to start like you can say oh you
practice in to develop wisdom yes where
you can say well look for these things
and you'll develop wisdom things such as
recognize experience of greed aversion
delusion in its manifestation so don't
try to negate that don't try to get rid
of it because by that by doing that
you're implying the sense of control
you're implying the ownership the master
you know this will this should not be
existing but instead discern thing
enduring in itself and that's how your
attitude towards you towards it will
become more apparent so I don't judge
answer is obviously you know it's
nothing wrong with it but it's quite a
roundabout way of just sort of telling
people well just keep doing it telling
that person just keep doing indeed sure
just keep doing it but more more
accurately more acutely stop trying to
get rid of things that are not your
responsibility and raccoon is very
responsibility is he gives us simile
just cover it he says from then on they
will just be arising and passing away in
this place the site the same same as
waves striking the seashore when a wave
comes in and finally reaches the
shoreline you just disintegrates and
vanishes a new wave comes and it happens
again the way of going the wave going no
further than the limits of the shoreline
in the same way nothing will be able to
go beyond the limits established by
one's own awareness if nothing can enter
through that door because you realize
nothing could have ever entered it's you
who was going out through the door and
being affected by things that are
outside so it was you who was stepping
from the
sure into the water that's being hit by
the waves that's exactly one thing but
you start discerning where your
responsibilities and then you don't
cross it so you realize the mind can
arise in all shapes and forms whatever
he wants
whichever way wants that's not the
problem there never was a problem you well
there never was a problem you well
communion and attaining it trying to get
rid of it that's where the problem is so
you stop doing that means that which
used to be a basis for acts of greed
still arises but there is no greed
because greed comes from you doesn't
come from things that we choose to be
basis for real will still arises but
there is no your will now in regard to
it so the way you still continue to come
and go but you don't get wet anymore
because you don't go outside where the
waves are you're recognized and people
start going outside or they carry on
going outside where you don't recognize
where the where the safety from the wave
is as well so you think I must prevent
waves from coming that's the only way to
remain dry but it isn't you just have to
see the range of the wave and allow it
to basically express itself so to speak
that's what I mean you to recognize
things in their manifestation they have
manifested on its own the wave has come
on its own so it's you who goes there
and tries to push the sea back that's
when you that basically that's what
person's question implied how do i how
do I like deal with this from an arising
so it doesn't arise because for him
automatically coming of the waves means
automatically me walking into the water
and getting wet he can't see the
difference between the two things means
flood means flood means what means
soaked drenched but if you recognize you
know the wave can come as like tsunami
wave it still can cross this line unless
I cross it that way and that's what I
mean that's where sensory strain will
enable you to start discerning that
without sense restraint yeah wave means
a bomb in the water either swimming with
it or trying to trying to go against it
so actually the simile is quite accurate
the similar is quite good because once
you start discerning that it's like like
finding that a single doorway through
which things come in because you invite
them in the island in the robot
or as the buddha gave the other one that
the town that surrounded by the wall and
there is only one point of entry and
exit and you realize well if i want to
keep track of what's going on inside I
don't need to chase people who come in
and go after people they go out I just
need to stay at the doorway the doorway
of that dead mindful context in regard
to feeling in reality perceptions in
regards intentions not the doorway of
focusing on the tip of your nose where
you're not aware of and that's basically
like you staring at the actual doorway
and you don't see who walks through the
doorway could you're staring at the
woodwork of it now you want to see ok
whoever comes in I know that it's in
because it's not a way of going up
so whatever manifests itself you know is
manifested to this extent and there is
lust in the mind in regard to it or
there is no lust in regard to now I
believe those things are still a problem
the problem is when you started
detaining their lust and then welcoming
it welcoming the prospect of what that
last is pointing at and that's how you
start acting out of the desire but if
you don't act out of desire any ill-will
those things cannot enter your mind even
when you actually act those things can
enter your mind that's why freedom from
those things is possible in the first
reason the choices it's not mine
choices online yeah well see people you
can eventually work your way up wherever
you see the actual present choice is not
being able to be owned by you but until
you work your way up in this gradual
manner what you're going to be doing is
denying the choice after you made it and
that's form of determinism like you made
the choice but then you say well there's
no self so this choice couldn't have
been mine well it was yours when you
were making it how do you know that it
was rooted in greed or aversion or
distraction and delusion and whenever
there is any of these three there is the
conceit there is sense of I am which
means it is your choice
so the the better way to go about it not
to kind of deny it in hindsight but
actually take it as a blanket rule that
the choice is always yours so through
that sense of responsibility for the
slightest choice you make you can then
eventually overcome the ownership of the
choice and responsibility would it not
remove the responsibility for the choice
so in order to all in order to remove
the ownership of responsibility you have
to stop denying responsibility and
people deny responsibility when they say
what choice is not mine nothing is mine
or people try to deny responsibility
when they try to prevent things they
were basis for the choices like the
question implied so as I'm sure pointed
out you have to stop well you have to
stop engaging with things on that level
but start discerning what you're doing
is and they stopped doing it and that's
that safe sure you find that it's
inaccessible to these waves so these
waves remain right in front of you
coming your way at full force but now
you have confidence that they can cross
because you know that they can't cross
because you stay with it long enough and
you saw that they can cross if you
haven't stayed with it long enough
well you're still doubt whether they can
cross or not which means you were
affected by it like you don't feel safe
if you doubt your safety you can't say
you're safe so the only way to stop
doubting your safety is to to December
that safety is in regard to these things
that are saving you but the natural
reaction is I must prevent these things
from a sailing in the first place that's
the true safety it isn't destroy them I
must destroy them I must I must remove
them rather than get to safety
exactly rather than actually hold on I
can't be fighting the sea and the waves
and the elements all I can do is find a
place where those elements can basically
can't set their foot in and that's when
a bond is that negative it's the
unmanifested I'm born it wasn't you
don't maintaining it of course not impossible
maintaining it of course not impossible
to maintain it impossible because
maintenance is on the level of intention
choice and this is safe in regard to
remember no you discern it in regard to
the threat
that's why requires no maintenance
because any manifestation is a threat
which means safety is a regard to any
threat which means it's in regard to any
manifestation so it's the independent
manifestation of thing which is not your
doing that maintains your sense of
safety which is equally not your doing
that's why our hand ship is effortless
once you develop it so you only need
manifestation you only need to work
initially to stop obscuring the true
nature of manifestations that it cannot
be owned because of that it's
impermanent that it's the unsatisfactory
because it doesn't have that sense of
pleasure connected with mastery over
things and because of that it cannot be
yours and it's not self there always
then that manifestation discerning a
thing it reveals all the time that's
safe design yes and that's the thing
once you fully understood it you don't
have to keep discerning it yeah but the
only like an aria Sarika needs to keep
discerning it Casteel because he still
has residues of habits of ignorance and
last and so on so he has to keep going
against their grain until it's fully
purified and then there is nothing with
the grain anymore I'm just saying this
so people don't the well note you mug
like like era hand is just constantly
this is a manifestation this is a man if
you know whatever you are aware of has
been manifested to that extent you're
fully aware of it already and to that
extent you fully free from it already
because there was nothing to affect you
in the first place
first thing fallen Aryan then would you
aware of it it reveals the island yes
yeah exactly the island is revealed by
the waves
yep so we need the island is outlined
yeah by the sea so yeah that's why the
the unborn like if the Seas born the
bond is the unborn the unmanifested so
from whatever it's manifested Nibbana is
outline but in here being the opposite
of that
- not defined undesignated is the extent
of man undetermined
yeah and by recognizing that you can't
recognize it okay exactly you can't go
back the other way and pretend you
haven't recognized that you you have
making out the extent of manifestation
yes yeah because there is the true
nature of manifestations they cannot
beyond they cannot be pleasurable that's
why you cannot be your own that is the
true nature and that's why liberation
from the ownership this answer self and
the dependence on pleasure is possible
because you actually get to discern and
then these things becoming conceivable
if those things were not truly beyond
the ownership unpleasant not your sense
of self they can be maintained in regard
to if they were not truly like that you
wouldn't be able to free yourself from
it the sense of self would be the master
and owner of the experience but that
means there wouldn't be any problem so
suffering but the fact that there is a
problem of suffering means the sense of
ownership is incompatible with that
that's why human existence is a
discrepancy between how things actually
are and how you are acting them to be
which is why you're responsible for
their being discrepancy
discrepancy any degree of discrepancy
determines the the degree we dig the
degree of liability towards the Duke are
there's no discrepancy no base for
dukkha that's our and that's why in the
scene there's just the scene a is just a
there's no discrepancy there now the
people sometimes get a sense of it but
then they look for the discrepancy at
the wrong place they look at the
discrepancy in the a and they try to
resolve a of discrepancy the scene must
be resolved of the lust in the version
illusion of the discrepancy of it but no
last in a version delusion is not in the
scene it's in your attitude towards it
that's where you remove that kind of
attitude you are and do it you
extinguish it and then what you have is
in the scene
there's just the scene in the herd
there's just that smell taste touch sea
salt thought but person's question
implied is oh there is a scene or greed
a version delusion how do I prevent it
from being seen so he didn't he didn't
see he doesn't see that the issue was in
his attitude towards the scene not the
scene so his question of trying to deal
with the scene prevent it make it not
make it unmanifest imply the wrong view
of him looking at the solution at the
wrong place here is another urgent charm
thoughtful clarity of insight this is
just one paragraph on that talk
so he says injustice the investigation
and development of insight into the
Dharma gives rise to this profound peace
of mind having gained such clear and
penetrating insight means it is
sustained at all times whether you're
sitting meditation with your eyes closed
or even if you are doing something with
your eyes open
whatever situation you find yourself in
be it in formal meditation or not the
clarity of insight remains when you have
unwavering mindfulness of the mind
within the mind
you don't forget yourself whether
standing walking sitting or lying down
the awareness within makes it possible
to lose makes it impossible to lose
mindfulness it's a state of awareness
that prevents you for getting yourself
mindfulness has become so strong that it
is self sustaining to the point where it
becomes natural for the mind to be that
way or as I say effortless Levens
these are the results of training and
cultivating the mind and it is here
where you go beyond doubt you have no
doubts about the future you have no
doubts about the past and accordingly
have no need to doubt about the present
either you still have awareness that
there is such a thing as past-president
future you are aware of the existence of
time there is the real reality of the
past president future but you are no
longer concerned worried about it hmm
that's right well you may keep saying
it's real as such may people would say
oh you must stop thinking about so
planning about the future look why time
is just a construction so what even if
it is it's a real as such it's real as a
construction your past is real as such
in the present your future plans are
real as such in the present you you
saying you must not worry about the
future is you worrying about the future
while you're saying you should not worry
about the future because you you clearly
saying manga must not plan the future
and you're planning to do that too not
plan the future so you are contradicting
yourself within that same sentence
and that's why you're wrong but if you
realize well what do you think about the
past or you think about a future you
cannot do that any differently than in
the present so if you're aware if you're
mindful of that inescapable basis of
being in the present means your past
your future everything else in between
is equally included within it it's real
as such and it was never an issue to let
go of the past that girl the future
means discern basically what has a
reason right what's enduring right in
front of you while you're worrying about
the past the future trying to deny to
stop thinking about it because you can
do that only the president
on the basis of the presently enduring
experience of whatever that experience
is and it's unwavering mindfulness well
that that would be the unwavering
mindfulness the mindfulness that doesn't
chase the content of your past the
content of the future or tries to get
super absorbed in the content of the
present instead he recognizes well
whether I want this to be or not it is
he has a reason and it's positioning and
in any movement I'm making regard to it
whether towards it away from it towards
the past towards the future it's only on
the basis of this thing's deepest of
this experience of being there and I'm
not saying that you start being mindful
of that that fundamental peripheral
context that oh oh my movements and
motions and plans and like intentions
feelings even perceptions in that manner
are on the basis of this thing still
being there this experience still
enduring on its own you start discerning
that you start developing mindfulness on
the right level and that's effortless
that is unwavering because it doesn't
the context doesn't waver in regard to
its content its other way around the
content get gets it its meaning from the
context
today there's a different mindfulness
and awareness well it's it's it's it's
it comes together mindfulness and
awareness you can't separate it that you
could think of awareness as being more
acutely mindful a mindfulness is being
mindful through through whether acutely
or broadly doesn't matter it's still
there so mindfulness and awareness it
goes hand in hand
sati something yeah yeah so in practical
terms I guess I don't know can take an
example well similar this you you you
like the future in example again but
you're worrying about something that's
gonna happen in two or three days but
your worry is right in the present you
don't need to wait for three days to
experience the worry on account of a
future prospect you're experiencing
right here right now in regard to the
future prospect so as such that future
prospect is real Oh as future that is
present to you as such and that's why
you can't be concerned about the future
or you can still grieve over the past so
you can't escape it in other words
that's why I'm saying if you're looking
at the content of your future account in
the past it's you you're bound by it in
the present and you have no choice about
that if you're looking at the content of
your present you're bound by it in the
cup in the present serials that was
never the problem things that happen to
you in the past the content off of
experiences that happen to you
good or bad traumas or blessings
whatever the content of the future
prospect that might happen to you some
of it will have to do you have no saying
that and there was never the problem the
problem was that in the present you were
exposed to suffering so even the future
dukkha is presently felt so from that
point of view du coeur is always in the
present like when when you think about a
future pain it's painful right now it
touches you right now so that's what I
mean you
you
presently can free yourself from
liability to future suffering but if
you're actually waiting for the future
content then you can free yourself right
here and now
so that has presently manifested and if
you understanding of that level that
that's where the problem is so the
problem is not in two or three days
what's going to happen to you the
problem is that you are affected by now
if you if you if you find a way to not
be affected by now you won't worry about
it in three days time either there's
like it's a meta meditation where you
imagine meeting a person that you don't
like well there's this meta meditation
it I've heard about you imagine a person
you don't like we're having problems
with think about them now so that when
you meet them you will have this meta
fully anger right well it's it's a long
dry lunch but it's not quite accurate
because you need to know what like the
problem is not a person the problem is
not meeting them or not meeting them the
problem is you are trying to presently
right here right now get rid of the day
unpleasant feeling that's always the
root of the problem
resistance to to the displeasure craving
for pleasure so when you think about the
future prospect meeting somebody in
three days then always upsets you and
hurts you that thing touches you know
because you meet that person you will
meet it that thing touches you because
you're trying to get rid of that
prospect right here right now and that's
why you suffer that's a Four Noble
Truths are always in the present its the
present insight one insight of craving
presence of craving means presence of
suffering so if I suffer now means I
crave now I don't crave in three days
time or I don't crave in ten ten years
ago sure I've done it back then and I
probably will do it in the future if I
don't become another hunt but craving is
always in the present that's where
suffering is always in the present and
that's if you approve that none of your
past changes and none of your future
needs to change either but that's why
you you can't worry on account of it
so it's it's not that you don't worry
about the future or believe over past
because you're so focused hard on the
present moment that nothing else exists
that's usually what people hope to do a
focus focus focus still and narrow my
field of vision so I don't see anything
before or after failing to see that no
matter how much you narrow it before and
after are always implied in the present moment
are always implied in the present moment
so whether your present moment is narrow
or wide there is past there is future
within it so you're just trying to shut
it down by trying to narrow on the
content of whatever is in front of you
that's usually where people think
meditation is focusing focusing focusing
focusing so I kind of lose the sight of
my past problems and don't overthink
future issues but once you realized it
doesn't matter if you if you still think
about a past but if you're always
thinking the future the problem is never
in those things the problem is in you
currently right here right now
persisting in an attitude of not wanting
I'm disagreeable be past be future being
present you remove the not wanting of
disagreeable that doesn't matter yeah in
three days I will meet this disagreeable
person but I'm not trying to get rid of
the disagreeable 'ti of that future
prospect right in our middle doesn't
matter what future well it doesn't
matter what I do doesn't matter what I
say I don't need to plan my actions I
don't need to rehearse my behavior I
don't need to go through psychotherapy
counseling sessions to plan how I will
act in the future all I need to do is
not crave presently to get rid of the
equally present prospect of disagreeable
and that's how future is in the present
already past is in the present that's
why previous issues they used to bother
you the you you used to grieve over
things that happen in the past
you kept grieving over it for years and
you will stop because grieving is always
in the present and then doesn't
literally doesn't mean doesn't matter
what happened to in the past you will be
unable to grieve over it
like the examples in the suitors of that
lady who whose husband died children got
one drowned there
by jackals reach the village parents
earthquake roof l killed him she lost
everyone in a course of one night he
emphasized and she went mad basically
exactly and that's like the the epitome
of the of the traumatized experience you
can imagine and she met the Buddha got
the teaching practice became another
hunt none of their changed her loss
hasn't changed the previous greens
haven't changed that she cannot grieve
over it anymore presently which is
always where the suffering was so again
it comes that simile again being an
island being in our future yep
what waves come memories of the past
doesn't matter it's only your lack of
clarity in regard to that that sort of
makes you affected by it not discerning
truly what an island is